# **FARHAD SADEGHLO**

Toronto, ON | 647-838-1420 | farhad.sadeghlo@gmail.com | https://www.linkedin.com/in/farhad-sadeghlo/ Machine Learning Project Articles Medium GitHub: https://github.com/farhad-sadeghlo

# Sr. Data Scientist | Big Data Analyst

Data Scientist with 5+ years of diverse experience in machine learning, database design, big data, and data analysis. Delivered technical solutions and reports to a wide range of enterprise customers. Supervised a team of 5 analysts and deployed machine learning-centric projects on time, making an MVP by agile methodologies. Recognized as a problem solver and a team player.

### **CORE SKILLS**

• ML and DL: Schikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Keras, Pandas

• Big Data Analytics: SQL, PySpark, Hive, Hadoop, Kafka

• Tools & Platforms: GCP, AWS, Linux

• **Programming:** Python, R

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Data Scientist, United Nations, Toronto, Canada

Aug 2021 - Present

- Designed data ETL pipeline on the cloud for data ingesting, cleaning, masking, and feature generation with a data integrity check (Azure Data Studio, PostgreSQL, CSV / JSON / XML).
- Conducted data standardization and deduplication based on string similarity (Levenshtein distance).

Lead Data Scientist, Omdena, Toronto, Canada

Jan 2020 – July 2021

Omdena Inc is a collaborative platform to build innovative, ethical, and efficient AI solutions to real-world problems. Hired as a machine learning engineer into a team of 45 from 25 countries and promoted to Lead ML Engineer in 6 months.

- Deployed anomaly detection API for clinical trial data of drug reactions to safeguard patients' health.
- Created topic modeling of the client's website, to ensure the web content is aligned with the business target (LDA, Gensim, PyLDAvis).

Career Note: The development journey was shared in engineering blogs: Article1, Article2, Article3

- Implemented a classification model for sexual abuse tweets detection (Naive Bayes, MLP, NLTK) Article
- Delivered analysis report and dashboard (Tableau) on employment loss due to the pandemic. Article

Data Scientist, EasyCM, Toronto, Canada

Sep 2017 – Mar 2020

<u>EasyCM</u> is an industrial machinery monitoring and diagnosis company supplying devices to companies in power generation, chemical, and petroleum engineering.

- Developed sale forecasting statistical models and analytical reports to increase revenue (Matlab)
- Identified new business opportunities leveraging Google Analytics on customers' behavior on webpages (Attribution Modeling).

# **SELECTED MACHINE LEARNING PROJECTS:**

#### **Recommender Systems**

- Architected two collaborative filtering and one content-based filtering projects to provide recommendations for books and products to offer similar items based on ratings and contents.
- Designed two projects; what hour of posting a post onto Hackernews website would receive more views, and what are profitable apps on both Apple and Google Play Store in terms of popularity and vacancy to start a new business.

## **Prediction and Classification**

 Predicted and classified delayed flights for LATAM Airlines with R-Squared 0.964, Accuracy 0.99, Recall 0.994, ROC\_AUC\_test 0.997, F1\_Score 0.996, MCC\_test 0.995.

# **Computer Vision**

• Experimented with a binary classifier based on 3-layer CNN architecture and achieved 92% accuracy in classifying airplane, car, and bird.

# **Big Data**

Practiced Hadoop, Hive, Kafka, and PySpark to gain working knowledge of Big Data technology

B.Sc. | Mechatronics Engineering, Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran

## **Data Analysis**

- Analyzed human activity features based on public health data (Samsung Health App) and delivered insights including lifestyle, health, and job quality (Dash, Plotly).
- Forecasted US central bank interest rate policy based on sequence signals from generative statistical models (Markov and Vasicek) fit on interest rates (LIBOR).

### **EDUCATION:**

Data Science student   Lantern Institute, Toronto, Canada	Aug 2019
M. Eng.   Mechanical engineering   Ryerson University, Toronto, Canada	
Aug 2017	

Dec 2009

# **CERTIFICATIONS:**

•	Introduction to Data Engineering (IBM)	Apr 2021
•	Explore stock prices with Spark SQL (Coursera Project)	Dec 2020
•	Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning	Mar 2020

#### **LEADERSHIP AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT:**

Toronto Machine Learning Society (TMLS), Associate Officer	Nov 2018 – present
ELEVATE, Associate Officer	Sep 2018 – Sep 2020
Canadian Society for Entrepreneurship and Innovation (CSEI), Industry Liaison	Sep 2017 – Mar 2019

#### **HONORS:**

Ryerson University Graduate Fellowship issued by the Faculty of the Mechanical and Industrial Engineering